

Hi! I'm Alex Pliutau

Energetic senior backend engineer with a passion for APIs, Cloud, Containers, distributed systems, microservices, currently living in Berlin.

Contact information

email <u>alex.pliutau@gmail.com</u>

Blogs <u>pliutau.com, packagemain Youtube channel</u>

Stackoverflow
Github
LinkedIn
Twitter

plutov
plutov
pltvs
pliutau

Phone +4915901497397 (Germany)

Nationality Belarus. Currently living in Berlin, Germany.

Objective

Professional software development with 8 years of experience bringing products from concept to release in a variety of environments and companies, applying <u>twelve-factor</u> methodology.

I know the full application cycle, from code to production practicing agile development methodologies.

Organizational and leadership skills garnered from multiple supervisory positions, including but not limited to: mentoring, appropriate delegation, flat organizational communication, task assignment & assistance.

Love challenges, clean code, concise documentation, clear communication and constructive feedback.

My biggest strengths are Backend, APIs, Containers, Web, Bots, Microservices.

Currently I like to use Go to build scalable and fault tolerant backend systems. Recently I started

my YouTube channel about programming in Go.

Languages

Belarusian Fluent

English Upper intermediate

Education

2007 - 2012 Belarusian State University of Informatics and Radioelectronics (Computer Science Bachelor's degree).

Job experience

12traits / Senior Software Engineer

January 2019 - Now

- Developing a Cloud-native backend for next-gen product using Microservices, Go, Kubernetes.
- Working closely with Data Science, UX, UI, Frontend teams to build a next-gen product.

24metrics / Technical Manager

October 2018 - January 2019

- Leading development of high load project to process 1b requests / day with Go backend.
- Fully automated CI / CD using Kubernetes and Spinnaker.
- Kubernetes-based environment deployed to GKE.
- Leading team of 3 engineers.
- Technical interviews, coding challenges.

Wizeline / Engineering Manager

May 2018 - September 2018

- Coordinate and direct projects, making detailed plans to accomplish goals and directing the integration of technical activities.
- Led > 100 technical interviews.
- Improving interview process, by preparing new on-site challenges.
- Running internal training programs.
- Projects bootstrapping.

Wizeline / Senior Software Engineer

March 2017 - May 2018

- Leading a team of engineers to build Facebook Messenger <u>Bot</u> for News.com.au, using Node.js for API, Wit.ai for NLU.
- Working with DevOps team to build the most suitable testing / production environment using Docker, Kubernetes and AWS ECS.
- Same backend platform was used later for Google Home Voice Bot.
- Building Google Home Voice Bot with AWS Lambda and Serverless.
- Building Air Quality Google Action with Go, GCP and Dialogflow.
- Building facial recognition office assistant using Go, Tensorflow. This project won local hackathon in 2018.
- Held few internal and public tech talks: Microservices with Go, The Art of Git.

Lazada / Senior Software Engineer

October 2014 - March 2017

- Leading development subteam in DevOps team. Lazada has a huge Microservices-based architecture (>100 services) and it requires tools and processes to manage it, DevOps team is a very important team there, responsible for downtime-less deployments, testing environments on Kubernetes, CI / CD on jenkins.
- Microservice Kit. Web and CLI project to create a new microservice based on a standard template, creates CI / CD jobs, assigns ports, adds middlewares, configures deployment. Golang, Docker, Kubernetes, Beanstalkd, Jenkins.
- Developed a tool for Data Migrations. Web tool to run data migrations / fixtures for deployments. Golang, MySQL, RabbitMQ.

Side Projects:

- <u>Weelco.com</u> Virtual reality project. REST API built in Go with Swagger and unit tests. Voice search with Translate API, Speech API, machine learning. VR video encoding, backuping, streaming. Ansible deployment, CDN API, Kubernetes. Prometheus for monitoring.
- <u>Logpacker.com</u> Cloud log management service, centralizes all logs from different devices into 1 system. Have a lot of options for data storage: Kafka, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Clickhouse, ElasticSearch. Built with: Golang, Kubernetes, gRPC, AWS, REST APIs.

Tuffle / Senior Fullstack Engineer

November 2012 - September 2014

- Managing a team of 6 engineers to build a fast-growing startup.
- Building "Another" social network based on user memories. It is a very interesting idea, but difficult to own the market. Technologies: PHP 5, Zend Framework 2, ffmpeg, REST APIs, MongoDB, Memcached.
- I was responsible for the whole application cycle: code, reviews, testing, infrastructure.

iTechArt / Software Engineer

August 2010 - October 2012

- Superb.net Rewriting old PHP 4.* code to Zend Framework, security optimizations, CSRF, XSS, SQL Injections.
- Cubique Open source datagrid built in Zend Framework, jQuery, HTML5, easily integrated into ZF.
- Clubautomation.com Large project written in Zend Framework 2, MySQL, jQuery. I was working in Backend team, developing new features, making site optimizations.